Daniel Emanuelsson, Ph.D.

Gothenburg, Sweden

■ d.emanuelsson@gmail.com

4 +46 76 776 6740

S daniel.emanuelsson

https://nz.linkedin.com/in/demanuelsson https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Daniel_Emanuelsson

https://github.com/demanuelsson

⊙ deman_v **У** DEmanV



Profile

Dr. Daniel Emanuelsson

I am a recent Victoria University of Wellington Earth Science doctorate. As a central part of multi-national teams and frontier research collaborations, I have gained extensive experience from several disciplines and my skills originate from both academia and client-oriented consulting. My research interests lie within the areas of climate dynamics; paleoclimatology; experimental design; laser spectroscopy; water stable isotopes; continuous flow analysis (CFA); decadal variability; tropical and midlatitude teleconnections with polar regions; atmosphere and sea-ice interactions; proxy/observational, data reanalysis/model comparisons; coastal and environmental processes; field campaigns; and data analysis.

Skills

Programming: Matlab, Fortran

Visualization: Matlab, GIS (ArcMap, esri)

Analysis Skills: Spatial and statistical analysis using global gridded datasets (e.g., reanalysis

products, GCM output). Time series analysis.

Languages: Excellent communication skills and proficiency in spoken and written English and Swedish (mother tongue).

Acted as reviewer for (journal reviews): Cryosphere.

Education

9/2011–9/2016 Doctorate Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand

Doctoral Thesis Title: High-Resolution Water Stable Isotope Ice-Core

Record: Roosevelt Island, Antarctica.

Supervisors: Dr. Nancy A. N. Bertler, Prof. James A. Renwick, and Dr. W.

Troy Baisden

External Examiners: Dr. Nerillie J. Abram, Australian National University,

and Dr. Adrian J. McDonald, University of Canterbury.

9/2007–12/2008 University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA

Group of Prof. Paul D. Quay, Chemical Oceanography

Key courses from the University of Washington: Global Carbon Cycle and Greenhouse Gases, Atmospheric Chemistry, Climate Extremes, Limnology,

Advanced Aquatic Ecology, Lake and Watershed Management, Fluid

Dynamics.

9/2002–8/2007 Master of Science in Engineering, Environmental and Coastal

Engineer, Lund's University of Technology (LTH), Sweden

Master Thesis Title: Impact of Coastal Erosion and Sedimentation along the

Northern Coast of Sinai Peninsula Supervisor: Prof. Magnus Larson

Coauthor Ali Mirchi

Examiner Prof. Hans Hanson

Professional Employment

11/2016–3/2017 Isotope Biogeosciences, National Isotope Centre (NIC), GNS Science,

New Zealand

Laboratory Technician

9/2011–9/2016 National Isotope Centre (NIC), GNS Science, New Zealand

PhD Student

Group of Dr. Nancy A. N. Bertler

1/2009–8/2011 **AECOM, Seattle, WA, US**

Coastal and Environmental Engineer

Group of Jena Gilman P.E. Senior Coastal Engineer

Major Projects:

Coquille River Jetty Condition Evaluation, Bandon, Oregon. Owner U.S.

Army Corps of Engineers

Lower Duwamish Superfund Site, Seattle, Washington. Owner City of

Seattle

Coastal Engineer, Inner Harbor Navigation Channel (IHNC) Hurricane Flood Protection, New Orleans, Louisiana. *Owner U.S. Army Corps of Engineer*

6/2005–9/2007 Tomelilla Municipality, Sweden

GIS Analyst and Survey Technician

Publications

Emanuelsson, B. D., N. A. N. Bertler, P. D. Neff, J. A. Renwick, B. R. Markle, W. T. Baisden, and E. D. Keller (2018a), The role of Amundsen–Bellingshausen Sea anticyclonic circulation in forcing marine air intrusions into West Antarctica, Clim. Dyn., doi: 10.1007/s00382-018-4097-3.

Emanuelsson, B. D., N. A. N. Bertler, P. D. Neff, J. A. Renwick, B. R. Markle, W. T. Baisden, and E. D. Keller (2018b), Southern Hemisphere ENSO-SAM dynamics captured in water isotopes (δD) from the Roosevelt Island Climate Evolution (RICE) ice core, Antarctica, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., In prep.

Emanuelsson, B. D., J. A. Renwick, N. A. N. Bertler, and P. D. Neff (2018c), The Influence of Southern Hemisphere Climate Variability on Water Isotopes from the Roosevelt Island ice core, Antarctica, J. Clim., In Prep.

Keller, E. D., W. T. Baisden, N. A. N. Bertler, B. D. Emanuelsson, S. Canessa, and A. Phillips (2018), Calculating uncertainty for the RICE ice core continuous flow analysis water isotope record, Atmos. Meas. Tech. Discuss., 2018, 1–20, doi:10.5194/amt-2017-387.

Bertler, N. A. N. et al. (2018), The Ross Sea Dipole -- temperature, snow accumulation and sea ice variability in the Ross Sea region, Antarctica, over the past 2700 years, Clim. Past, 14(2), 193–214, doi:10.5194/cp-14-193-2018.

Winstrup, M. et al. (2017), A 2700-year timescale and accumulation reconstruction for Roosevelt Island, West Antarctica, Clim. Past, In review.

Emanuelsson, D. (2016), High-Resolution Water Stable Isotope Ice-Core Record: Roosevelt Island, Antarctica: a thesis submitted to the Victoria University of Wellington in fulfilment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy (Geology) / by B. Daniel Emanuelsson., Thesis (Ph.D.)--Victoria University of Wellington, 2016.

http://researcharchive.vuw.ac.nz/bitstream/handle/10063/6699/thesis access.pdf?sequence=4

Emanuelsson, B. D., W. T. Baisden, N. A. N. Bertler, E. D. Keller, and V. Gkinis (2015), High-resolution continuous-flow analysis setup for water isotopic measurement from ice cores using laser spectroscopy, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 8(7), 2869–2883, doi:10.5194/amt-8-2869-2015.

Tuohy, A., N. Bertler, P. Neff, R. Edwards, D. Emanuelsson, T. Beers, and P. Mayewski (2015), Transport and deposition of heavy metals in the Ross Sea Region, Antarctica, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., 120(20), 10,11,911-996, doi:10.1002/2015JD023293.

Emanuelsson, B. D., J. Gilman, and J. Orlins (2011), Jetty Condition Evaluation Report for the Coquille River Jetty Condition Evaluation Report for the Coquille River, Prep. U.S. Army Corps Eng., 126.

Emanuelsson, D., A. Mirchi, and M. Larson (2007), Impact of Coastal Erosion and Sedimentation along the Northern Coast of Sinai Peninsula, Lund's University of Technology (LTH).

Field and Lab Work Experience

2012, 2013, and 2014 RICE ice core processing continuous flow analysis (CFA) lab campaigns

11/2012– 1/2013 Roosevelt Island, Antarctica. RICE ice core drilling (0–130 m)
11/2011– 1/2012 Roosevelt Island, Antarctica. RICE ice core drilling (130–760 m)

9/2008 University of Washington's vessel R/V *Thomas G. Thompson*. Research

cruise Seattle to Hawaii

1/2002– 3/2002 Yacht Crew Member, Atlantic Ocean and Mediterranean Sea Crossing

Scholarships

9/2011– 9/2015 PhD Rutherford Scholarships (Victoria University of Wellington)

9/2007– 12/2008 Valle Scholarships (University of Washington)

International Conferences

12/2014 AGU conference San Francisco, USA (Poster)

8/2014 Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research (SCAR) conference (Talk)

■ Memberships in Professional Associations

American Geophysical Union (AGU)

Association of Polar Early Career Scientists (APECS)

Qualifications and Training

Driver's license: Swedish, US and New Zealand

Swedish coastal skipper certificate class VIII

Dr. Daniel Emanuelsson

■ d.emanuelsson@gmail.com

□ +46 76 776 6740

Referees

Prof. James Renwick

Physical Geography, Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand.

+64 4 463 4719

James.Renwick@vuw.ac.nz

Prof. Troy Baisden

Lake and Freshwater Science, University of Waikato, Hillcrest, Hamilton, New Zealand.

+64 7 838 4055

Troy.Baisden@waikato.ac.nz